Guide to the William E. Irwin Photograph Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Portraits of American Indians, circa 1893-1903; Series VIII; 1.25; (1 box)
  Series VIII is organized into six subseries: Exterior Portraits of Identified Individuals, Exterior Portraits of Unidentified Individuals, Interior Portraits of Unidentified Individuals, Studio Portraits of Identified Individuals; Studio Portraits of Unidentified Individuals, and Studio Photographs of American Indian Artifacts
  This series chiefly consists of portraits of American Indians, including exterior portraits, interior portraits, and studio portraits. It also includes studio photographs of American Indian artifacts.
  Views of American Indians at identified locations in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory are in Series VII.
  - Exterior Portraits of Identified Individuals
    - Exterior portrait of Geronimo posed sitting, holding a J. H. Dance and Brothers .44 caliber revolver, and wearing a feathered war bonnet, probably in Indian Territory, 1897; 4 unmounted photographic prints (Box 9, Folder 524)
    - Exterior portrait of Geronimo posed sitting, holding a J. H. Dance and Brothers .44 caliber revolver, and wearing a feathered war bonnet, probably in Indian Territory, 1897; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 525)
    - Exterior portrait of Geronimo posed sitting, holding a J. H. Dance and Brothers .44 caliber revolver, and wearing a horned headdress, probably in Indian Territory, 1897 (Box 9, Folder 526)
      5 unmounted photographic prints (1 hand-colored) and 2 photographic postcards
    - Exterior portrait of three American Indian men, identified left to right as Silverhorn (Haungooah), a Kiowa Indian; Anko (Ankopaaingyadete, In the Middle of Many Tracks), a Kiowa Indian; and Comanche Jack (Watchymansookwat), a Comanche Indian, probably in Oklahoma Territory, circa 1890; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 527)
    - Exterior portrait of a Comanche Indian woman posed sitting on a blanket, identified as Lena Fisher, probably in Oklahoma Territory, circa 1899; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 528)
    - Exterior portrait of a Comanche Indian man, identified as Red Bird, posed standing with a horse, probably in Oklahoma Territory, circa 1899; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 529)
    - Exterior portrait of an Comanche Indian man, identified as Arko, posed standing with fur-wrapped braids with a Comanche Indian woman, identified as Arko's wife, seated behind him on the grass, probably in Oklahoma Territory, 1899; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 530)
    - Exterior portrait of a Kiowa Indian man, identified as Gum Bye (or Gumbye), posed sitting between two Kiowa Indian girls, identified as his daughters, wearing buckskin dresses with elk teeth decorations, as well as two additional girls posed sitting on the ground; they are posed in front of a tipi with a brush enclosure, probably in Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 531)
    - Exterior portrait of an elderly Kiowa Indian woman, identified as the mother of Lone Wolf, posed sitting on a rug on the ground, probably in Oklahoma Territory, circa 1886; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 532)
    - Exterior portrait of a Comanche Indian woman, identified as Lena Fisher, posed standing next to a blanket hanging on an arbor, probably in Oklahoma Territory, circa 1899; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 533)
  - Exterior Portraits of Unidentified Individuals
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian woman posed standing in an American Indian camp, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 cabinet photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 534)
      Inscription on recto of cabinet photograph: "Irwin & Mankins, Chickasha and Duncan, I.T."
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man and American Indian woman, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 cabinet photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 535)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian woman holding an American Indian infant on her lap in front of a tipi, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 536)
      Inscription on recto of mounted photograph: "Irwin, Chickasha, Ind. Ter."
    - Exterior portrait of five Kiowa Indian children seated outside of a tipi, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 cabinet photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 537)
      Inscription on recto of cabinet photograph: "Irwin, Chickasha, Ind. Ter."
    - Exterior portrait of six Kiowa Indian children seated in an American Indian camp or village, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 cabinet photograph (Box 9, Folder 538)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man with fur-wrapped braids posed standing with a horse, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 539)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man with fur-wrapped braids posed standing next to a river, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 540)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man with fur-wrapped braids posed standing next to a river, facing away, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 541)
    - Exterior portrait of eight American Indian boys posed sitting on a wooden stoop with an American Indian girl partially visible on the right, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 542)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian girl and American Indian woman holding an infant in a cradleboard next to an arbor, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 543)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man with fur-wrapped braids posed sitting on a tree stump, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 544)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man posed standing next to an arbor, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 545)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man wearing a peace medal and posed standing on a rug, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 546)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man posed standing beside an arbor, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 547)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man and two American Indian women posed standing near an arbor, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 548)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man and an American Indian woman posed standing with a boy, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 549)
    - Exterior portrait of a young American Indian man and an American Indian woman posed sitting on a wooden porch, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 550)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man posed sitting with an American Indian woman and two American Indian girls in front of a tipi and arbor; one of girls holds a doll in a small cradleboard, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 551)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian woman posed sitting with two American Indian girls in front of a tipi and arbor; one of girls holds a doll in a small cradleboard, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 552)
    - Exterior portrait of two American Indian women posed standing in front of a tipi, one woman also carries an infant on her back, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 553)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian girl wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decoration and posed sitting, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 554)
      Inscription in negative: "16"
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian girl wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decoration and posed sitting with an American Indian boy posed standing, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 555)
      Inscription in negative: "27"
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man wearing a suit and posed sitting with an American Indian woman with an infant on her back and an American Indian girl, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 556)
    - Exterior portrait of a Comanche Indian woman posed sitting on the ground with a tipi and tents in the background, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1899; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 557)
      Inscription in negative: "113"
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian or racially mixed woman wearing American Indian dress and posed standing near a river with a light-haired infant on her back and an American Indian girl, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 558)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian girl posed sitting near a river, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 559)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian girl and American Indian boy posed standing by a tipi; both children wear rosary beads and buckskin clothing, and the boy also wears a wrapped forelock, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 560)
    - Exterior portrait of two American Indian women posed standing in front of a grass structure, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 561)
    - Exterior portrait of two American Indian women posed sitting and one standing on a wooden porch in front of pieces of floral fabric, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 562)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian woman posed standing under a tree and holding on to a branch, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 563)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian woman posed sitting with an American Indian boy at her feet and a horse in the background, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 564)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian woman posed standing next to a tipi with a cradleboard on her back and facing partially away from the camera, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 565)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian boy with fur-wrapped braids posed sitting on a log; a Durham tobacco pouch is partially visible in his vest pocket, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 566)
    - Exterior portrait of a Kiowa Indian girl posed sitting and wearing a dress with elk teeth decorations, as well as holding a doll in a small cradleboard, in front of a wooden structure, probably in Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 567)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian boy posed standing and wearing non-native clothing, as well as holding a bow and arrow, in front of two dogs and tipis in the distance, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 568)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian girl posed sitting and looking away from the camera with a tipi in the background, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 569)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian girl posed standing and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decoration in front of a tipi, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 570)
    - Exterior portrait of an American Indian man wearing a feathered war bonnet and posed standing in a hay stack, as well as holding a revolver, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 571)
    - Exterior portrait of two Comanche Indian girls posed standing in front of tipis, probably in Oklahoma Territory, circa 1899; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 572)
  - Interior Portraits of Unidentified Individuals
    - Interior portrait of an American Indian woman, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 573)
    - Interior portrait of an American Indian woman posed sitting on a bed with American Indian artifacts decorating the wall behind her, probably in Indian Territory or Oklahoma Territory, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 574)
  - Studio Portraits of Identified Individuals
    - Studio portrait of American Indian man, identified as Poor Buffalo's Son, circa 1893-1903; 1 photographic print mounted and 1 photographic print unmounted (Box 9, Folder 575)
    - Studio portrait of two Kiowa Indian women, identified as Millie Oytant and Cora, posed standing, wearing buckskin dresses, the latter dress decorated with elk teeth, circa 1893-1903; 1 cabinet photograph and 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 9, Folder 576)
      Printed on recto of cabinet photograph: "Marvin Irwin, Marlow, I.T."
    - Studio portrait of two Kiowa Indian women, identified as Millie Oytant and Cora, posed standing, wearing buckskin dresses, the latter dress decorated with elk teeth, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 577)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian woman, identified as Millie Oytant, Kiowa, posed sitting and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decorations, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photograph and 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 9, Folder 578)
      Printed on recto of mounted photograph: "Irwin, Chickasha, I.T."
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian woman, identified as Cora, posed standing and wearing buckskin dresses with elk teeth decorations, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 579)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian woman, identified as Cora, posed sitting and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decorations, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 580)
    - Studio portrait of an American Indian woman and a man, identified as William Edward "Ed" Irwin, circa 1893-1903; 1 cabinet photograph (Box 9, Folder 581)
      Printed on recto: "Irwin & Mankins.. ."; missing portion of the mount
    - Studio portrait of a Cheyenne Indian woman, identified as Gertrude Threefinger, posed sitting and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decorations, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photograph and 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 9, Folder 582)
      Printed on recto of mounted photograph: "Irwin, Chickasha, Ind. Ter."
    - Studio portrait of three American Indian women and an American Indian man, woman on far right identified as Martha Nahawat, a Kiowa Indian, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 583)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian man, identified as Lone Wolf the Younger (Delos K. Lone Wolf, Mamay-Day-Te or Mamay-Dat-Ta), posed sitting at a table and wearing a suit, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 584)
    - Studio bust portrait of a Kiowa Indian man, identified as Lone Wolf the Younger (Delos K. Lone Wolf, Mamay-Day-Te or Mamay-Dat-Ta), posed sitting and wearing a suit, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 585)
    - Studio portrait of a Comanche Indian man, identified as Essapunnua (John Whiteman or John White Man), posed sitting and holding a feathered gourd rattle, circa 1893-1903; 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 9, Folder 586)
    - Studio bust portrait of a Comanche Indian man, identified as Essapunnua (John Whiteman or John White Man), posed sitting and holding a feathered gourd rattle, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 587)
    - Studio portrait of four Kiowa Indian men posed sitting and standing, wearing suits; identified left to right, standing, Doyeto and Jim Waldo, and sitting Poolaw, Lone Wolf the Younger (Delos K. Lone Wolf, Mamay-Day-Te or Mamay-Dat-Ta), circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 588)
    - Studio portrait of four Kiowa Indian men posed sitting and standing, wearing suits; identified left to right, Poolaw, Jim Waldo, Doyeto (standing), and Lone Wolf the Younger (Delos K. Lone Wolf, Mamay-Day-Te or Mamay-Dat-Ta), circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 589)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian man, identified as Poor Buffalo, posed sitting and wearing a feathered war bonnet and holding an eagle-tail fan, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 590)
    - Studio portrait of an Comanche Indian man, identified as White Wolf, posed kneeling and holding a Model 1894 Marlin rifle, as well as wearing a feathered war bonnet and fur hair wraps, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 591)
    - Studio portrait of two American Indian men respectively posed standing and sitting, wearing suits and hats; Kiowa Indian man on the left identified as Lone Wolf the Younger (Delos K. Lone Wolf, Mamay-Day-Te or Mamay-Dat-Ta), circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 592)
    - Studio half portrait of a Kiowa Indian man, identified as Lone Wolf the Younger (Delos K. Lone Wolf, Mamay-Day-Te or Mamay-Dat-Ta), posed sitting and wearing a suit, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 593)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian man, identified as White Buffalo, posed sitting and wearing a fringed buckskin suit and fur hair wraps, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 594)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian man and woman, identified as White Buffalo and his wife, posed standing; he wears a fringed buckskin suit and fur hair wraps, and she wears a fringed buckskin dress, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 595)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian family, identified as the family of White Buffalo, with White Buffalo posed sitting between his wife and daughter posed standing; he wears a fringed buckskin suit and fur hair wraps, and they wear fringed buckskin dresses, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 596)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian family, identified as the family of White Buffalo, with White Buffalo posed sitting next to his wife posed sitting on the floor and his daughter posed standing; he wears a fringed buckskin suit and fur hair wraps, and they wear fringed buckskin dresses, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 597)
    - Studio portrait of a Comanche Indian man, identified as Moohie Tatsah, posed standing and wearing fur hair wraps, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 598)
    - Copy photograph of an exterior portrait of a Comanche Indian man, identified as Quanah Parker, posed standing on the porch of a wooden building with two Comanche Indian women, identified as his two wives, To-pay (Toe-Pay) and Cho-ny (Chony or Chonie), probably at Fort Sill, Indian Territory, circa 1893-1903; 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 9, Folder 599)
      One photographic print includes printed text: "We will remain two more weeks in Richmond."
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian woman, identified as Anna E. "Kiowa Annie" Jones Berry, posed sitting in a low chair and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decoration, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 600)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian woman, identified as Anna E. "Kiowa Annie" Jones Berry, posed standing and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decoration, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 601)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian woman, identified as Anna E. "Kiowa Annie" Jones Berry, posed sitting and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decoration, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 602)
    - Studio portrait of a Comanche Indian woman, identified as Mabel Mahseet, posed sitting with her upper body through a picture frame, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 603)
    - Studio bust portrait of a Cheyenne Indian woman, identified as Gertrude Three Finger, posed sitting and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decoration and wrapped braids, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 604)
    - Studio portrait of two Kiowa Indian women, identified as Amie and Carrie, posed standing and wearing cradleboards on their backs, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 605)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian woman, identified as Lissie Woodward, posed standing next to a cradleboard resting on the ground that holds a Kiowa Indian infant, identified as Oliver Woodward, circa 1893-1903; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 606)
  - Studio Portraits of Unidentified Individuals
    - Studio portrait of two Kiowa Indian girls posed standing and sitting, and wearing buckskin dresses with elk teeth decorations, circa 1893-1903; 1 cabinet photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 607)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian girl posed standing with her hands behind her head and wearing a buckskin dress with elk teeth decorations, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 608)
    - Studio portrait of an American Indian infant in a cradleboard, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 609)
    - Studio portrait of an American Indian infant in a cradleboard, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 610)
    - Studio portrait of an American Indian woman posed standing and wearing a cradleboard with an infant, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 611)
    - Studio portrait of an American Indian woman posed standing next to a cradleboard with an infant, circa 1893-1903; 1 mounted photograph and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 612)
    - Studio portrait of an American Indian man posed standing and wearing a feathered war bonnet, circa 1893-1903; 1 cabinet photograph and 1 mounted photographic print (Box 9, Folder 613)